<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Charles R. Charles by the grace of God king of Scotland, England, France and Ireland, Defender of the faith. To our lovits ... Whairas we have by many fair and calme waies, and alanerly by them endevoured to reclaime our subjects ...</title>
            <title>Proclamations, 1639-04-25.</title>
            <author>Scotland. Sovereign (1625-1649 : Charles I)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1639</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 14 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11719</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 22003</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S100630</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99836462</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99836462</idno>
            <idno type="VID">738</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11719)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 738)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1584:08)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Charles R. Charles by the grace of God king of Scotland, England, France and Ireland, Defender of the faith. To our lovits ... Whairas we have by many fair and calme waies, and alanerly by them endevoured to reclaime our subjects ...</title>
                  <title>Proclamations, 1639-04-25.</title>
                  <author>Scotland. Sovereign (1625-1649 : Charles I)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>3 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted by Robert Young, His Majesties printer for Scotland,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno Dom[ini] M.DC.XXXIX [1639]]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Robert Young worked as a printer in London and Oxford in 1639.</note>
                  <note>Cf. Steele 1700 (Scotland).</note>
                  <note>Royal arms 223, with 9 lines of shading between 'HONI' and 'SOIT'.--STC.</note>
                  <note>A revision of STC 22002, also published in London, 1639, and ordered suppressed by King Charles in favor of this proclamation.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="royal_declaration">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:738:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <head>C R</head>
                  <q xml:lang="frm">HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENSE</q>
                  <figDesc>depiction of the English royal blazon surmounted by a crown and with a single, crowned royal initial (C, R) on its left and right, respectively</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <signed>Charles R.</signed>
               <lb/>
               <signed>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>HARLES by the grace of God King of Scotland, England, France and Ireland, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender of the faith.</signed> 
               <salute>To Our Lovits <gap reason="blank" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈1 span left blank〉</desc>
                  </gap> Heraulds, Maiſſers, Meſſengers, Purſevants, Our Scheriffes in that part conjunctly and ſeverally ſpecially conſtitute, greeting.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Whairas We have by many fair and calme waies, and alanerly by them endevoured to reclaime Our ſubjects, but eſpecially ſuch as (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing cunningly ſeduced by vthers) have blindly run themſelffes into undutiful and ſedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious courſes, And have laboured by the ſame faire means to re-eſtabliſch and ſattle Our Royall authoritie and governament there; but hitherto all in vaine, Our clemencie and mildneſſe towards them producing no better effects in many of them, then increaſe of thair inſolencies towards Us, and ſuch ane height of violent rebellion, as taking Our Royall Forts and Caſtles, with Our Crowne, and all Our ancient Regall Ornaments, munition for warre, and whatſoever belongs to Us, and forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying of Townes againſt Us: Yet We heartily declair and faithfully promittis, that though We be now in airmes, they ſall be no wayes uſed, either to force upon this Our native Kingdome any innovation in Religion, or to infringe any the civill liberties or lawes thairof: for ſuch is Our tender affection both to it, and to ſuch of Our ſubjects there as have ſchawn themſelffes loyall and faithfull to Us at this time (who both may expect and ſall receive ſuch teſtimonies of Our favour as thair fidelitie juſtly merites) as we ſall ever have a great and ſpeciall caire both of it and them, accomp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting it Our glorie to preſerve liberty and freedome amongſt them, according to thair lawes.</p>
            <p>Thairfore We doe once againe by this, renew Our former promiſes for the maintenance of Religion and Lawes, and We aſſure all Our people that We will make guid whatſoever We have declaired or publiſched in any of Our Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamations or Declarations, or which Our Commiſsioner declaired in Our name at the laſt pretended generall Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly; And this We doe in all ſinceritie of heart; and withall to make it appear, both at home and abroad, that the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and deteſtable malice of theſe ſeditious men (which firſt raiſed theſe ſtormes) had no true ground to worke upon, whill they ſought to poyſon the hearts of Our guid people, and to make them beleive We did not only intend to bring in Poperie, but that We were that way inclined Our Selffe. Now though it be not neceſſarie for Us to make often De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarations of Our integritie to the true reformed proteſtant Religion, which We from Our heart profeſſe, yet We hold it fit thus farre to manifeſt to all Our people and to the world, that this thair allegation is notoriouſly fals, and that they could have no vther end thairin, then by broching that fond and ſcandalous report, to ſteill away the hearts of Our guid and loyall ſubjects, that ſo they might both with more eaſe and greater ſecuritie be able to compaſſe thair awn traite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and damnable deſignes, to the overthrow of all Monarchicall governament; Whairas We take God (the ſearcher of all hearts) to witneſſe, that as We are Defender of the true Proteſtant Religion, which We from Our heart profeſſe, ſo We truiſt by his guidneſſe and mercie We ſall continue in the ſame all Our dayes, and never permit any innovation of Religion to creep into this or any vther of Our Kingdomes, but ſall conſtantly maintaine the ſame, as it is eſtabliſched, according to Gods law, and by the lawes and conſtitutions of Our ſeverall Kingdomes reſpectively.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:738:2"/>
            <p> Now whairas We ſay We will conſtantly maintain the true Religion by law eſtabliſched in theſe Our Kingdomes, and cannot tell how to expreſſe Our ſelffes either better or vtherwiſe, to the full content of Our guid people (as We are moſt willing to doe it) yet We are informed that ſome captious, buſie, and traiterouſly affected men, labouris (even out of this fulneſſe and clearneſſe of Our expreſsion) to poyſon Our loyall ſubjects, and makes them believe that it is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt We have no intention to performe what We have promiſed; Theſe thairfore are further (if further We can goe) to aſſure all Our guid people, that Our intentions all of them are Regall, juſt, and full of integritie. And ſo farre are We from intending to breake any the leaſt peece of a promiſe which We have made unto them, as that We ſall moſt pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually and ſtrictly obſerve all We have promiſed, and that as firmly as We ſall adhere to the Religion it ſelfe. And heir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon We hope and are perſwaded that all Our guid and loving ſubjects, notwithſtanding the whiſpers of ſeditious men, will both believe and reſt ſatisfied with the integritie of Our intentions in this behalffe, and be no more abuſed and led out of the way of their alledgeance by the treacherous practices of theſe men, who being exceeding foule them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelffes, labouris to get as many followers as they can, and theirby hopes to eſcape the juſt puniſchement which their trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terous carriadge hath deſerved: But We muſt let them and Our guid people knaw, that to ſeduce many is the worſt way they can take to make themſelffes innocent, and the greater inducement to make Us inflict due puniſchement on them; yet We thinke it withall very neceſſary for Us to let all Our people and the Chriſtian world knaw, That though the number be very great whoſe carriadge hath been treaſonable in this commotion, yet ſuch is and ſall be Our clemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie towards them, as yet We ſall freely pardon and forgive all ſuch amongſt them, as ſall lay hold on this Our mercie offered them, and from hencefuirth carry themſelffes dutifull to Us and Our juſt commands. And to this end We en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend (God willing) to hold Our Parliament ſo ſoon as We ſall ſee the countrey in ſuch peace and quietneſſe, as may befit Our honour in Perſon to come amongſt them: And thairfore We command all Our Houſes, Forts and Caſtles, ſurpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and taiken by any of Our ſubjects, and detained by them, Our Crowne, Royall Ornaments of Our Regall power, munition for warre, and all things whatſoever belonging to Us, and taiken by any of Our ſubjects, to be reſtored unto Us within eight dayes after the publication heirof, And all the ſaids fortifications of townes to be razed and demoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed to the ground, at leaſt the beſt they can doe to that purpoſe within the ſame ſpace; And alſo all the lands, houſes, or guids of Our loving ſubjects, who have beene faithfull unto Us, and are taiken from them by any whoſoever, to be reſtored unto them within the ſame ſpace; which We command to be done, as they tender thair alledgeance. And We doe alſo command all and every one of Our ſubjects to lay downe airmes, and all their forces and airmies to be diſſolved and diſsipate, and ilk man to repaire in peaceable manner to the place of his ordinary dwelling, And all conventions, conventicles, and convocations of Our ſubjects, of what qualitie or degree ſoever they be, to ſurceas in time comming within the ſaid ſpace and dayes after the publication heirof, as they tender thair alledgeance; All which being done, and Our ſaids ſubjects randring unto Us their civill and dewtifull obedience in all things, conforme to the lawes of this Our native Kingdom, We give full and free pardon to all Our ſaids ſubjects and every one of them, of all facts and deeds done by them or any of them preceding the day and daite of the publication heirof, And further ſall cauſe ane Act of oblivion to be maide heirupon in Our next enſuing Parliament. And ſince We have been pleaſed out of Our innate, Royall and tender affection We beare to this Our native Kingdome, to cure the wounds of the diſtracted eſtaite thairof with ſo gentle a balme, and to paſſe by the errours and diſorders thairof with ſo faire a hand, and to embrace (even the moſt rebellious) in the airmes of Our mercie, Wee are confident that this Our gracious and free offer ſall be heartily and with all ſubmiſsive dewtie received by Our ſubjects: But if the perverſe diſpoſition of ſome be ſuch as they will not be cured, but ſtill goe forward in thair crooked and rebellious waies, and (without due reſpect to the alledgeance they owe unto Us their native and lawfull King) ſall not accept of this Our free grace and pardon, before the expiring of the ſaid eight dayes, which We hope none will doe, then and in that caſe (the time being expired, and Our grace and pardon contemned, by diſobeying of theſe Our juſt and lawfull commandements) We are forced to have recourſe to ane more ſcharpe and quick way, to cure thair obſtinacie and rebellion by the ſword of juſtice: And thairfore in that caſe We doe proclaime all ſuch as ſall reject this Our free and gracious pardon, and does not returne before the expiring of the ſaids eight dayes to their civill and dutifull obedience, to be from thencefuirth open Rebels and Traitours to Us Our Crowne and dignitie, And declaire all their lands and poſſeſsions, guids and geir, to be forfaulted to Us and Our Crowne, and that We ſall diſpoſe of thair lands, poſſeſsions, guids and geir, to Our weill-deſerving ſubjects, Noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, Gentlemen, and vthers, who ſall adhere to Us and obey Our juſt commands. And to this purpoſe We diſchairge all vaſſals and tenants to any Rebels, from making paiment to them of any thair rents, dewties, or caſualities, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire them to keepe the ſame in thair hands, the one halfe whaireof ſall be kept for Our uſe, the other halfe for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelffes: promiſing alſo to the tenants of the ſaids Rebels, who ſall leave their Maiſters and aſsiſt Us to the mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of Our authoritie, guid termes of yeares in the eſtaits they poſſeſſe, with the diminution of the thrid at leaſt, if not more, of the dewties they pay, as We ſall finde them to deſerve by thair guid ſervice and readie obedience unto Us, And to the vaſſalls of ſuch ſuperiours as are Rebels, that they ſall become Our immediate tenants and vaſſals, and hold thair lands and poſſeſsions of Us, and that for the paiment of the thrid part leſſe dewtie then is conteinit in thair preſent charters and they preſently pay to their ſuperiour; providing they adhere to Us, and aſsiſt not their diſloyall ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periours, but leave them and concurre with Us for maintenance of Our authoritie. And if the ſuperiour be loyall, and
<pb facs="tcp:738:3"/>the vaſſals and tenants refuis this Our grace, and to adhere to Us, or to concurre with the ſaid ſuperiour in Our ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, We declaire it ſall be leſum to the ſaid ſuperiour to expell the vaſſalls and tenants thus rebellious, fuirth of thair lands and poſſeſsions, and what ſall accres to Us by the forfalture of thair lands and poſſeſsions, We freely diſpone and totally reſigne it to the loyall ſuperiour, promiſing to concurre and aſsiſt him for effectuating heirof. And further We diſchairge all debtours who are addebted in ſummes of money to any the ſaids Rebels, to make paiment to them of the ſummes of money addebted to them, or any part thairof, Aſſuring Our guid ſubjects that they ſall have retribution out of the ſame monies as We ſall finde them to deſerve. And further we declaire, whatſoever Burrough or Citie ſall em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace this Our free pardon and grace, and adhere to Us, and aſsiſt Us in the maintenance of Our authoritie, We doe heirby take them, thair liberties and priviledges, into Our protection and favour, and ſall defend the ſaids Cities and Burrowes in thair rights and priviledges, as becommeth ane juſt King, Secluding them alwayes from all hope of ſuch favour at any time thairafter, in caſe they doe not embrace this Our free grace and pardon before the ſaids eight dayes ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pired. And laſt, it is Our pleaſure, and We heirby do declaire, that the forfalture or eſcheite of any of the Rebells, ſall not prejudge Our guid ſubjects who adhere to Us, or embraces this Our free grace, and behave themſelffes as dutifull ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects heirafter, but that the lands and eſtaites of the ſaids Rebels, and the gifts of forfalture and eſcheite proceeding from thair rebellion, ſall be burdened with the payment of the juſt debts addebted to Our guid ſubjects, and they firſt payed before any thing accres to Us or Our donatour, And execution ſall paſſe upon thair bands and obligations, in the accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomed manner, againſt the lands and guids of the ſaids Rebells.</p>
            <p>OUR WILL is thairfore, and We charge you ſtrictly, and commands, that incontinent theſe Our Letters ſeene, you paſſe and make publication heirof by open Proclamation, at the Mercat Croſſes of the head Burrows of this Our Kingdome of Scotland, and all other places needfull, whairethrough none pretend ignorance of the ſame.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven at Our Court at Yorke <date>the twentie fifth day of April 1639.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Imprinted by ROBERT YOUNG, His Majeſties Printer for Scotland, <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> M.DC.XXXIX. CUM PRIVILEGIO.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
